NYSUT Vice-President's Office, Maria Neira Files. 6174/016
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Vice-President's Office Maria Neira Files
1987-2008
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
Neira, Maria
6174/016
7 cubic feet
7 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
As vice president of New York State United Teachers, Maria Neira oversees the union's initiatives on educational policy and is NYSUT's frontline advocate to the New York State Board of Regents and the State Education Department. At her direction, the NYSUT Education & Learning Trust, the union's professional development arm, has strengthened and expanded educational opportunities for teachers and other school staff. Neira was appointed by President Obama to serve on the President's Advisory Commission on Educational Excellence for Hispanics. She also serves on the Congressional Hispanic Caucus Institute Advisory Council. She is a member of the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards and the founding publisher of Educator's Voice. An AFT vice president, she also serves as a vice president of the New York State AFL-CIO Executive Council and as a member of the Board of Directors of the AFL-CIO's Workforce Development Institute. She is a member of the New York State Workforce Investment Board, the Greater Capital Region United Way Board of Directors, Capital District's 100 Hispanic Women, the Labor Council for Latin American Advancement and the National Association of Latino Elected Officials Education Fund. She directs NYSUT's fundraising as a statewide flagship sponsor for American Cancer Society programs, including the Making Strides Against Breast Cancer annual walks in which union volunteers have raised millions for the cause. She has served on many state committees, including the governor's Children's Cabinet Advisory Board and the State Committee of Practitioners, and is a member of several other professional organizations. Neira is a recipient of the Ellis Island Medal of Honor from the National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations, the Educational Leadership Award of the National Puerto Rican Day Parade and the YMCA Northeast New York Woman of Achievement Award. She has been honored by the United Federation of Teachers Hispanic Affairs Committee, the Hispanic Latino Cultural Center, Long Island Latino Teachers Association, the Schenectady Hispanic Heritage Committee and the Girl Scouts of Northeastern New York. She previously served as assistant to the president on education issues for the United Federation of Teachers, NYSUT's affiliate in New York City public schools, where she directed a wide range of education initiatives and helped develop strategic plans for education reform. She also served as director of the UFT's Special Educator Support Program. Neira began her teaching career in New York City in 1977 and was a fourth-grade bilingual teacher at the Bilingual Bicultural Mini School in Manhattan. Neira holds a B.A. and an M.S. from Hunter College of the City University of New York.
7744995
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
P. Leary, July 18, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 04, 2014
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
As vice president of New York State United Teachers, Maria Neira oversees the union's initiatives on educational policy and is NYSUT's frontline advocate to the New York State Board of Regents and the State Education Department. At her direction, the NYSUT Education & Learning Trust, the union's professional development arm, has strengthened and expanded educational opportunities for teachers and other school staff.
Neira was appointed by President Obama to serve on the President's Advisory Commission on Educational Excellence for Hispanics. She also serves on the Congressional Hispanic Caucus Institute Advisory Council. She is a member of the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards and the founding publisher of Educator's Voice.
An AFT vice president, she also serves as a vice president of the New York State AFL-CIO Executive Council and as a member of the Board of Directors of the AFL-CIO's Workforce Development Institute. She is a member of the New York State Workforce Investment Board, the Greater Capital Region United Way Board of Directors, Capital District's 100 Hispanic Women, the Labor Council for Latin American Advancement and the National Association of Latino Elected Officials Education Fund. She directs NYSUT's fundraising as a statewide flagship sponsor for American Cancer Society programs, including the Making Strides Against Breast Cancer annual walks in which union volunteers have raised millions for the cause. She has served on many state committees, including the governor's Children's Cabinet Advisory Board and the State Committee of Practitioners, and is a member of several other professional organizations.
Neira is a recipient of the Ellis Island Medal of Honor from the National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations, the Educational Leadership Award of the National Puerto Rican Day Parade and the YMCA Northeast New York Woman of Achievement Award. She has been honored by the United Federation of Teachers Hispanic Affairs Committee, the Hispanic Latino Cultural Center, Long Island Latino Teachers Association, the Schenectady Hispanic Heritage Committee and the Girl Scouts of Northeastern New York.
Neira previously served as assistant to the president on education issues for the United Federation of Teachers, NYSUT's affiliate in New York City public schools, where she directed a wide range of education initiatives and helped develop strategic plans for education reform. She also served as director of the UFT's Special Educator Support Program. Neira began her teaching career in New York City in 1977 and was a fourth-grade bilingual teacher at the Bilingual Bicultural Mini School in Manhattan.
Neira holds a B.A. and an M.S. from Hunter College of the City University of New York.
Biographical / Historical
The Vice President's Office directs NYSUT's initiatives on educational policy and is its frontline advocate to the New York State Board of Regents and the State Education Department.
The Vice President's Office oversees the Division of Research and Educational Services, created in 1974, and the Education and Learning Trust (called the Effective Teaching Program until 2005), NYSUT's professional development arm.
Maria Neira was elected First Vice President in 2005 after serving as Second Vice President for six months; she succeeded Antonia Cortese, who had been First Vice President since 1985 after serving as Second Vice President since 1973. Cortese left NYSUT in 2004 to become executive vice president of the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). Maria Neira also serves as a vice president of the AFT.
In 2007, the titles First Vice President and Second Vice President were changed simply to Vice President, with the duties of each carried over to the officers who held the former respective positions. Maria Neira remains the director of the divisions and programs traditionally under the first vice president's purview, and also coordinates NYSUT's fundraising activities for the American Cancer Society.
Vice President Kathleen Donahue, elected second vice president in 2005, oversees Program Services, which addresses the needs of NYSUT's health care professionals, members of small and rural locals, new members and retirees. It also provides training in workplace health and safety issues.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/001: NYSUT President's Office Files. 6174/002: NYSUT Vice-President's Office Files. 6174/017: NYSUT General Officers Records 6174/017 AV: NYSUT General Officers Audio-Visual Materials 6174/017 P: NYSUT General Officers Photographs 6174/018: NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, Maria Neira Files. All other 6174 collections
Teachers' union, New York (State); Neira, M. (Maria); New York State United Teachers; New York State United Teachers. Archives
7744995
- Academic Bill of Rights Talking Points, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Memo to Maria Neira with bullet points re movement by the political right across the country to enact state and federal laws threatening academic freedom of faculty under guise of student free speech, replacing peer review with potentially politically driven government review of institutional accreditation; list of states with pending legislation; samples of proposed legislation in Florida state legislature and U.S. House of Representatives; resolution and position paper by American Federation of Teachers (AFT), "Opposition to Outside Control Over Academic Decision Making Under the Banner of Intellectual Diversity," and "House Higher Ed Bill Is a Step Backward, Says AFT," noting some remedies to alleged liberal bias would require hiring of Republicans to faculties; How a Bill Becomes a Law in New York State
- Administrative Committee (formerly Managers) 12/14/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Tickler questions for facilitators re closing the achievement gap; memos re meeting; issue of NEA Advocate, December-January 2005-2006
- Administrative Committee 12/07/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Meeting notice
- Administrative Committee 9/21/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Agenda; communications checklist for managers; memo re release time for volunteers for post-Hurricane Katrina relief efforts, September 20; NYSUT constitution with redline changes in anticipation of merger with NEA; handwritten notes
- Administrative Committee re LM-30 Form, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Confidential attorney-client memos re filing of required Department of Labor Form LM-30, March-June; instructions for filing; form; related correspondence
- Administrative Committee PAC Lists, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Cover memo to Administrative Committee re Political Action Committee binder updates; memo to PAC coordinators, March 14, 2005; list of duties and responsibilities of PAC members, revised 1/30/03; Local Presidents List by Senate District; list of Retiree Council presidents; list of Committee of 100 by Senate District; lists of members of NYS Senate and Assembly; list of NYSUT Board of Directors; list of labor relations specialists assigned to locals
- Administrative Committee 3/29/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Agenda for NYSUT/BOCES District Superintendent Committee, March 22, 2005; memo from vice president Maria Neira alerting K-12 local presidents of Regents proposal to raise passing grade for Regents exams to 65, NYSUT's "serious concerns" about it, March 28, 2005; related position papers
- Advanced Placement (AP), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Letter to the editor from NYSUT vice president Maria Neira in Albany Times-Union, "Don't Overlook Minority Success in AP Courses," February 2, 2005; 2004 AP Overview Report in New York City schools by ethnic breakdown and by gender, overall and by subject
- American Cancer Society Colorectal Cancer, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Fact sheets re colorectal cancer and wrist band campaign; memos re NYSUT purchase of bands
- American Cancer Society Gala of Hope 3/11/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Flyer, journal tribute rate sheet, and honorary committee commitment form for Gala of Hope event, with cover memo to NYSUT president Tom Hobart from ACS executive vice president, requesting full-page ad, February 15, 2005
- American Cancer Society Making Strides Against Breast Cancer Walk 08/2/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Fact sheet re walk; suggestions for activities for team coordinators; text of remarks at kickoff breakfast; printed invitation to 2005 NYSUT Kickoff Breakfast; memos
- American Cancer Society Making Strides Against Breast Cancer Walk Contract, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Correspondence re NYSUT sponsorship of Making Strides Against Breast Cancer walk; list of number of NYSUT walkers and donations raised at each event location in 2004; list of breakfast dates and locations in October 2005; 2004 NYSUT/ACS Making Strides Against Breast Cancer letter of agreement; letter from vice president Maria Neira to NYSUT officers requesting authorization of payment for previous year's contract commitment, noting ACS had not billed for it, May 12, 2005; letter from American Cancer Society executive vice president, thanking Neira for checks for 2004 and 2005 sponsorship, June 15, 2005
- American Cancer Society STARS, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Correspondence re School Teams Achieving Results Successfully (STARS) recognition program; press release from Statewide Center for Healthy Schools re first annual awards ceremony, sponsored by NYSUT, October 1, 2004; program for First Bi-Annual New York Healthy STARS Awards Ceremony, September 30, 2005; brochures and related materials for 24/7 Let's Go! Healthy Lifestyle Program, by NYSUT
- AFL-CIO see under NYS AFL-CIO
- AFT Collier Support Personnel Hearing, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Statement of Facts submitted by Florida Education Association re investigative proceeding re failure to transmit per capita dues by Collier Support Personnel, AFT Local 7412, January 4, 2006; FEA Governance Documents: Constitution, Bylaws & Transition Agreement as amended May 2004; correspondence; handwritten notes
- AFT Executive Council 7/6/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Agenda
- AFT Executive Council Unionism and Democracy Seminar, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Letters to AFT vice president Maria Neira from executive director of Albert Shanker Institute re seminar, "Unionism & Democracy: The Experience, the Legacy, the Future," scheduled for April 20-21; related correspondence
- AFT Executive Council Conference Call 09/1/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Memos re conference call; ballot, memo re federal court decision, and related materials re rescission of decision to create an administratorship for Federacion de Maestros de Puerto Rico and revoke charter for nonpayment of per capita dues
- AFT Healthcare May 2-3, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Memo re Leadership Development Conference for school nurse members of AFT locals, January 25, with attached information sheet
- AFT Job Training Improvement Act, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Letter from AFT to House Education and Workforce Committee, opposing the Job Training Improvement Act of 2005, asserting that it would undermine the Workforce Investment Act, divert scarce job training resources from unemployed individuals and eliminate dislocated worker programs, February 16, 2005
- AFT Latino Caucus 6/16/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  "Solidaridad!" AFT Latino Caucus New York Chapter 1st Annual Scholarship Dinner Dance Program, June 16, 2005; invitation; correspondence re ad purchase
- AFT LULAC (League of United Latin American Citizens) 6/30/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Printed program for 76th LULAC National Convention, "Emerging Latino Communities: Strengthening America," June 27-July 2, 2005; presentation transparencies and disk for session on No Child Left Behind, "Education Policy Today: A Report Card on Latinos"; flyers re No Child Left Behind; AFT policy brief, "NCLB: Its Problems, Its Promise," July 2004; English and Spanish versions of brochure, "Pathways to Success: An AFT Guide for Parents"
- AFT NALEO (National Association of Latino Elected and Appointed Officials) June 23-25, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Correspondence re NALEO 22nd Annual Conference; presentation transparencies and disk re No Child Left Behind; AFT policy brief, "NCLB: Its Problems, Its Promise," July 2004
- AFT NEAFT Partnership Joint Council, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Joint communiqu about seventh meeting, held on March 17
- AFT No Child Left Behind (NCLB) Task Force 9/28/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Letter from Massachusetts governor Mitt Romney to the state legislature with attached Act to Reform Education, September 22, 2005; policy brief by National Center for Research on Evaluation, Standards, and Student Testing: "Fixing the NCLB Accountability System," summer 2005; memo from NYSUT executive vice president Toni Cortese re materials for NCLB Task Force meeting, including outline of questions to be discussed, September 21, 2005; spreadsheet, NCLB Continues to Challenge Schools in 2005, listing Adequate Yearly Progress (AYP) status by state, percent of schools needing improvement, percent of students who scored at or above proficient on state tests, and other measures compared with 2004; description of the No Child Left Behind Reform Act (S. 724) by Sen. Christopher Dodd; description of the No Child Left Behind Improvement Act; article by Stateline.org, "Higher Bar Tripping Schools," August 12; list of proposals to amend NCLB's AYP formula; explanations of selected proposals to fix AYP; related memos. See also No Child Left Behind; see also Committee of Practitioners.
- AFT NCLB Task Force Meeting 5/3/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Agenda; background materials, including Center on Education Policy report, articles re tutoring, restructuring from Education Week, New York Times, Wall Street Journal, National Journal, Philadelphia Inquirer, Chicago Tribune; article by AFT president Edward McElroy, "NCLB's Unintended Consequences," in American Teacher, May/June 2005; AFT list of NCLB restructuring strategies; AFT booklet, "Redesigning Low- Performing Schools: It's Union Work," 2001
- AFT NCLB Action Agenda 2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Bound "AFT Action Agenda for the No Child Left Behind Act, prepared for AFT Pre-K- 12 Local Presidents," March 2005; press release, "NCLB Let's Get it Right: Union Announces National Campaign to Educate Public and Elected Leaders on Improving the No Child Left Behind Law," May 19, 2005
- AFT NCLB Task Force 2/24/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Agenda; minutes of NYSUT Task Force on Value-Added Accountability/Assessment, February 9, 2005; copy of Time cover story, "What Teachers Hate about Parents," February 21, 2005; newsletter, Title I Report: Compensatory Education's Comprehensive News Source, January 2005; Federal Funds Information to States VIP Series lists of grants to states, February 2005; list of funding shortfalls by state, from Office of the Democratic House Leader, "Republicans Break Their Promise on Education Funding," September 9, 2004
- AFT Paraprofessionals and School-Related Personnel Conference March 31 - April 3, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Tentative 28th annual PSRP conference schedule: "Moving the Union On"
- AFT Teachers Program and Policy Council Meeting 5/19-20/05 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Agenda; chair's report; related meeting materials re charter schools, secondary school reform, English Language Learners; AFT press release re No Child Left Behind. See also (NYSUT) Policy Council.
- AFT Teachers Program and Policy Council Meeting 10/20-21/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Agenda; chair's report; related meeting materials; AFT draft resolution on English Language Learners, October 4, 2005; draft resolution on elevating the practitioner voice in secondary school reform; list of members of AFT Program & Policy Council, 2005-2006; letter to Rep. John Boehner, chair of Committee on Education and the Workforce, from AFT president Edward McElroy, opposing Family Education Reimbursement Accounts, asserting that it would divert needed funds away from victims of Hurricanes Katrina and Rita, October 19, 2005, with attached AFT Proposal under the Provisions of No Child Left Behind to Aid Students Displaced by Hurricane Katrina; documents, Standards for Responsible and Responsive Teacher Unions; minutes of AFT Teachers Program & Policy Council, May 19-20, 2005; CD-ROM, Welcome to Teaching from the AFT; NYSUT Policy Council notes for the October meeting
- AFT State Federation Presidents Conference November 16-19, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Tentative agenda; program; text of Columbia State Federation case; memos re travel arrangements
- AFT Video 7/22/05, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Memo re filming of AFT video to include NYSUT officers' overseas visit
- Auditor see Zimmerman
- Bargaining Units Retreat Planning Committee, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Agenda for November 14, 2005, meeting; handouts for NYSUT Manager's Retreat, June 7-8; correspondence
- NYSUT Benefit Trust Meeting 9/13/03, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Minutes of June 29, 2003, meeting; notification of September 13 meeting
- NYSUT Benefits Conference November 5-6, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Conference program
- Board of Directors Reception Dinner and Meeting December 9-10, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 36)